<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>arm on Lukáš Zapletal</title><link>https://blog.zapletalovi.com/tags/arm/</link><description>Recent content in arm on Lukáš Zapletal</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 17 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.zapletalovi.com/tags/arm/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Booting 3.8+ kernels on Marwell Kirkwood ARM Zyxel NSA 310</title><link>https://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2013-03-17-booting-38-kernels-on-marwell-kirkwood-arm-zyxel-nsa-310/</link><pubDate>Sun, 17 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2013-03-17-booting-38-kernels-on-marwell-kirkwood-arm-zyxel-nsa-310/</guid><description>Zyxel NSA 3xx are excellent and cheap NAS devices and finally support for model NSA 310 landed in Linus tree in the 3.8 version. Good news, but this Marwell Kirkwood-based ARM device is using DTS (Device Tree). I had no experiences with compiling DTS kernels, until this night.
So the Device Tree, or The Flattened Device Tree, (FDT) is a data structure for describing the hardware in a system. It is a derived from the device tree format used by Open Firmware to encapsulate platform information and convey it to the operating system.</description></item><item><title>ARM - procesory budoucnosti?</title><link>https://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2011-01-07-arm-procesory-budoucnosti/</link><pubDate>Fri, 07 Jan 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2011-01-07-arm-procesory-budoucnosti/</guid><description>Před nějakým rokem jsem kdesi na fóru psal o budoucnosti Linuxu a těsné návaznosti na procesory ARM. V té době se pouze polemizovalo o nějakém masovějším nasazení této architektury v mobilech a internetových přístrojích. Měl jsem (a mám) za to, že Linux na desktopu potáhne nahoru právě architektura ARM (a všelijaké tablety/netbooky a jiná zařízení). A proč?
Microsoft Windows na ARMu nefungují. Tedy - abych byl přesný. Microsoft slibuje, že nové Windows 8 na ARMu poběží.</description></item></channel></rss>