<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>libvirt on Luk치코 Zapletal</title><link>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/tags/libvirt/</link><description>Recent content in libvirt on Luk치코 Zapletal</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 20 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://blog.zapletalovi.com/tags/libvirt/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Accessing libvirt VMs via telnet</title><link>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2018-02-20-accessing-libvirt-vms-via-telnet/</link><pubDate>Tue, 20 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2018-02-20-accessing-libvirt-vms-via-telnet/</guid><description>There are many &amp;ldquo;tricks&amp;rdquo; floating around how to connect to VM when you have a networking issue and ssh is not available. The idea is to use serial console to get shell access. Here is how to do this properly with RHEL7 host and guest.
First, create a VM with serial console configured with remote TCP server. There are multiple options, I find TCP server in &amp;rsquo;telnet&amp;rsquo; mode the most flexible configuration because most scripting languages has the protocol built-in.</description></item><item><title>EFI with libvirt in RHEL7</title><link>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2017-10-03-efi-with-libvirt-in-rhel7/</link><pubDate>Tue, 03 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2017-10-03-efi-with-libvirt-in-rhel7/</guid><description>RHEL 7 does not ship with EFI firmware by default, at least version 7.4 I just tested with. There is easy help tho if you want to try EFI in libvirt which does not make much any other sense than for development purposes.
We will follow steps from Fedora Wiki but changed into RHEL context. Download firmware repository which have latest builds of EFI QEMU firmware and NVRAM images:
# wget -O /etc/yum.</description></item><item><title>How to setup testing virtual network in libvirt</title><link>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2012-04-05-how-to-setup-testing-virtual-network-in/</link><pubDate>Thu, 05 Apr 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2012-04-05-how-to-setup-testing-virtual-network-in/</guid><description>From the last week I am working on Katello (systems management software for subscriptions and content) and Foreman (system management software for provisioning and configuration) integration. I need to get everything running on one physical box using libvirt. I had to do three rounds until I finally configured everything correctly (actually doing my third round now). Anyway, let me share one libvirt-related idea that came to my mind today.</description></item></channel></rss>