<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>music on Luk치코 Zapletal</title><link>https://blog.zapletalovi.com/tags/music/</link><description>Recent content in music on Luk치코 Zapletal</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 07 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.zapletalovi.com/tags/music/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>How to convert song to YouTube</title><link>https://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2019-02-07-how-to-convert-song-to-youtube/</link><pubDate>Thu, 07 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2019-02-07-how-to-convert-song-to-youtube/</guid><description>I wrote few songs, mostly dance music (house, techno) years go. Since now I don&amp;rsquo;t have time for this (I wish) I only listen to my music from time to time. I realized I haven&amp;rsquo;t uploaded any of my songs to YouTube yet. There is one particular I would like to upload. I was searching for a command to convert an audio (OGG Vorbis in my case) to MP4 Yoube-friendly format with a cover art.</description></item><item><title>My remix appears on the most listened album on Jamendo</title><link>https://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2011-07-15-my-remix-appears-on-most-listened-track/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 Jul 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2011-07-15-my-remix-appears-on-most-listened-track/</guid><description>I am happy to do one exciting announcement today. I just found out remix of my track On The Moon called Walz Into The Moonlight is featured on the most listened album on Jamendo across all coutries and all the time (as of July 2011). It's called Listen (track no 12). I released the original track on ccMixter in 2005, site for sharing audio content licensed under Creative Commons.</description></item><item><title>Spinning season has started</title><link>https://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2011-06-15-spinning-season-has-started/</link><pubDate>Wed, 15 Jun 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2011-06-15-spinning-season-has-started/</guid><description>Just few years before I used to sping records in clubs, halls and festivals. I started with techno in ten years ago, then bought bunch of drum and bass plates, to collect house records just few years later.
These days I only play on my friends parties over the summer. It&amp;rsquo;s relaxing and fun. And the time is finally here again. I am going to remove the dust from my turntables, records, headphones and other equipment now.</description></item></channel></rss>