<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>rhel6 on Luk치코 Zapletal</title><link>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/tags/rhel6/</link><description>Recent content in rhel6 on Luk치코 Zapletal</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 19 Jul 2012 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://blog.zapletalovi.com/tags/rhel6/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Rsync in cron</title><link>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2012-07-19-rsync-in-cron/</link><pubDate>Thu, 19 Jul 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2012-07-19-rsync-in-cron/</guid><description>I've installed some rsync scripts to a RHEL6 cron yesterday, but this morning I was surprised with error messages in my mailbox:
/etc/bashrc: fork: retry: Resource temporarily unavailable
/etc/bashrc: fork: Resource temporarily unavailable
rsync: connection unexpectedly closed (0 bytes received so far) [receiver]
When you see resource temporarily unavailable you can be sure it is most likely some system limit issue, or your box is really running out of resources (worse case).</description></item><item><title>Getting TP-LINK TL-WN722NC work under RHEL6</title><link>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2012-05-05-getting-tp-link-tl-wn722nc-work-under/</link><pubDate>Sat, 05 May 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2012-05-05-getting-tp-link-tl-wn722nc-work-under/</guid><description>TP-LINK TL-WN722NC is a wonderful and cheap USB wifi stick which provides stable connection and has extra USB cradle bundled with it (so you can put it on a window or something). I have to admit there are better solutions than USB sticks, but sometimes you need to solve a problem and this ten bucks piece of hardware can do it for ya.
Unfortunately the driver (ath9k_htc) is still in testing, thus not available in default RHEL6 kernels.</description></item><item><title>Connect to your ssh boxes faster</title><link>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2011-05-28-connect-to-your-ssh-boxes-faster/</link><pubDate>Sat, 28 May 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2011-05-28-connect-to-your-ssh-boxes-faster/</guid><description>If you want ultra-fast connection login times to your ssh servers you may like to change several values in the /etc/ssh/sshd_config file along with RSA authentication:
GSSAPIAuthentication no
UseDNS no
You can use this only if you don't need GSS or reverse DNS of course. No more delays. Every milisecond counts!</description></item><item><title>Export for both NFS v4 and v3 clients under RHEL 6</title><link>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2011-05-28-export-for-both-nfs-v4-and-v3-clients/</link><pubDate>Sat, 28 May 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2011-05-28-export-for-both-nfs-v4-and-v3-clients/</guid><description>One of the new features in RHEL 6 is NFS version 4. It has a different concept and some administrators can be confused. I highly recommend to read RHEL 6 Storage Administration Guide or other documents related to NFSv4.
The key change in NFSv4 is the concept of the root directory. To get things working for both v4 and v3 clients the most recommended way is to remount everything under one directory (we will create /exports for that).</description></item></channel></rss>