<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>pulp on Luk치코 Zapletal</title><link>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/tags/pulp/</link><description>Recent content in pulp on Luk치코 Zapletal</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 25 Oct 2011 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://blog.zapletalovi.com/tags/pulp/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>How to easily mount ISO files for Apache</title><link>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2011-10-25-how-to-easily-mount-iso-files-for/</link><pubDate>Tue, 25 Oct 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2011-10-25-how-to-easily-mount-iso-files-for/</guid><description>I play with yum repositories and ISO files very often, therefore it is vital to have such files and directories avaiable via local Apache httpd. I had this idea of mounting ISO files into directories and using these as yum repositories. I leveraged fuseiso program, but there's a trick.
Fuseiso works per-user by default and few steps need to be done to publish those directories under different (apache) user. The solution is to use allow_other FUSE option:</description></item><item><title>Red Hat Update Infrastructure 2.0</title><link>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2011-08-22-red-hat-update-infrastructure-20/</link><pubDate>Mon, 22 Aug 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2011-08-22-red-hat-update-infrastructure-20/</guid><description>Last month Red Hat released Red Hat Update Infrastructure 2.0. It is a collection of technologies that offers cloud providers the ability to easily deploy Red Hat solutions into their environments. Cloud solution providers can use Red Hat Update Infrastructure to give their customers the ability to update Red Hat technology in the cloud.
Red Hat Update Infrastructure streamlines the deployment of Red Hat technologies into a cloud environment. Initial configuration, initialization, and synchronization of available instances in the cloud are done with very little user configuration or intervention.</description></item></channel></rss>