<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>gnome-shell on Luk치코 Zapletal</title><link>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/tags/gnome-shell/</link><description>Recent content in gnome-shell on Luk치코 Zapletal</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 30 May 2012 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://blog.zapletalovi.com/tags/gnome-shell/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Disable Window Animations updated for Fedora 17</title><link>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2012-05-30-disable-window-animations-updated-for/</link><pubDate>Wed, 30 May 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2012-05-30-disable-window-animations-updated-for/</guid><description>Few weekends ago, I've updated my Gnome Shell plugin Disable Window Animations for Fedora 17 (Gnome Shell 3.4). If you switch workspaces often, you might find this handy. I switch them thousands time a day, this saves me time &amp; eyes. Like it? Say thanks in the comments.
This extension simply disable all window manager animations: window "slide-ins" and workspace "slide-ups" and "slide-downs". However, it does not disable dash animations ("</description></item><item><title>Disable animations Gnome Shell plugin now as extension</title><link>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2011-12-29-disable-animations-gnome-shell-plugin/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Dec 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2011-12-29-disable-animations-gnome-shell-plugin/</guid><description>Heya, you may already noticed the new site extensions.gnome.org for Gnome Shell extensions. It is possible to install extensions with a single mouse click with the latest and greatest version.
I just put my Disable Window Animations extensions there, so you can easily install from the service.
It is available here: https://extensions.gnome.org/extension/119/disable-window-animations/
Enjoy and HNY!</description></item><item><title>Gpaste terminal integration</title><link>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2011-12-02-gpaste-terminal-integration/</link><pubDate>Fri, 02 Dec 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2011-12-02-gpaste-terminal-integration/</guid><description>Sometimes I need to copy whole output of some program into my clipboard or selection. I use nice Gnome Shell extension called Gpaste (packages gpaste and gnome-shell-extension-gpaste in Fedora and Red Hats). It is a nice daemon, command line tool and Gnome Shell menu, everything well integrated.
And how to do that? It is easy. Just pipe it through the gpaste command, I am not kidding.
$ echo "Some very long output"</description></item><item><title>How did I tune my Verne</title><link>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2011-11-10-how-did-i-tune-my-verne/</link><pubDate>Thu, 10 Nov 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2011-11-10-how-did-i-tune-my-verne/</guid><description>So I am basically done with tuning my new installtion of Fedora 16 Verne. Let me summarize this a little bit over here now.
Gnome Shell Extensions
Before I can start I have to bind F1-F4 keys to swtiching workspaces one to four. It's pretty easy to do it in the Gnome 3 keyboard settings, but the thing is you can only bind numbers 2, 3 and 4 when they exist.</description></item><item><title>New gnome-shell extension - disable-window-animations</title><link>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2011-07-21-new-gnome-shell-extension-disable/</link><pubDate>Thu, 21 Jul 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2011-07-21-new-gnome-shell-extension-disable/</guid><description>I have created new Gnome Shell extension called disable-window-animations. It's very simple. It disables all window manager animations like Window "slide-ins", Workspace "slide-ups" and "slide-downs" and many more... :-)
However it does NOT disable dash animations (Window-key "zoom-ins" and "zoom-outs" etc.)
I change workspaces very often and it was driving me crazy. There was no way of disabling it. Monkey patch did help here. Enjoy.</description></item><item><title>Gnome Shell and transient notifications</title><link>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2011-07-13-gnome-shell-and-transient-notifications/</link><pubDate>Wed, 13 Jul 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2011-07-13-gnome-shell-and-transient-notifications/</guid><description>I like that Gnome Shell is mostly written in JavaScript. It allows cool and easy hacking.
I am using weechat for my IRC chatting. Since I am running it on a server (via ssh) and I want to be notified about highlights and private messages, I am using simple rnotify.tcl plugin that sends notifications over (tunneled) tcp to local server that calls notify-send command. Easy setup that just works.</description></item><item><title>Make Gnome Shell more usable</title><link>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2011-07-01-make-gnome-shell-more-usable/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Jul 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2011-07-01-make-gnome-shell-more-usable/</guid><description>Evaluating Gnome Shell for the second time. There are few things driving me crazy. All can be easily fixed.
1) Multiple workspaces works only on primary monitor. If you have two (or more) screens setup forget changing workspaces on secondary ones. It just does not work(TM). Easy fix: run gconf-editor, navigate to /desktop/gnome/shell/windows and uncheck workspaces_only_on_primary. Restart with alt-f2 and "r" + enter.
2) Window "slide" animation when changing workspaces is killing me.</description></item></channel></rss>