<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>foreman on Luk치코 Zapletal</title><link>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/tags/foreman/</link><description>Recent content in foreman on Luk치코 Zapletal</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 30 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://blog.zapletalovi.com/tags/foreman/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Denormalizing PostgreSQL join tables</title><link>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2021-08-30-denormalizing-postgres-join-tables/</link><pubDate>Mon, 30 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2021-08-30-denormalizing-postgres-join-tables/</guid><description>Foreman OpenSCAP plugin stores security scanner results in Foreman&amp;rsquo;s PostgreSQL database providing integrated UI, API and CLI experience. To simplify our use case, let&amp;rsquo;s assume that each report has many-to-many association to security rules with some result (pass or fail). This gives us two main SQL tables: report and rule and a join table between them. For simplicity, let&amp;rsquo;s ignore the result which should be an extra column in the join table.</description></item><item><title>Finding the right cost for bcrypt/pbkdf2</title><link>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2021-05-11-finding-the-right-cost-for-bcryptpbkdf2/</link><pubDate>Tue, 11 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2021-05-11-finding-the-right-cost-for-bcryptpbkdf2/</guid><description>Foreman uses bcrypt with variable cost as the default password hashing approach, but I learned that bcrypt is not approved for passwords by NIST the other day. Before finishing my patch, I wanted to see what are the sane iteration counts for PBKDF2-HMAC-SHA algorithm which is approved by NIST. Here are results to give you rough estimation from my Intel NUC i3 8th gen running i3-8109U, a CPU from 2018:</description></item><item><title>Human readable name generator</title><link>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2016-03-07-human-readable-name-generator/</link><pubDate>Mon, 07 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2016-03-07-human-readable-name-generator/</guid><description>Out of ideas for incoming bare-metal host names in your cluster? I wrote a little generator which contains frequently occurring given names and surnames from the 1990 US Census (public domain data):
256 (8 bits) unique male given names 256 (8 bits) unique female given names 65,536 (16 bits) unique surnames Given names were filtered to be 3-5 characters long, surnames 5-8 characters, therefore generated names are never longer than 14 characters (5+1+8).</description></item><item><title>Image based deployment via dd and nbd</title><link>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2015-11-20-image-based-deployment-via-dd-and-nbd/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2015-11-20-image-based-deployment-via-dd-and-nbd/</guid><description>My train to Pilsen had about 300+ people onboard and apparently super-modern ultra-fast WiFi technology can&amp;rsquo;t handle that many people. At least when administrator sets C class IPv4 network. People have cell phones, tablets and laptops. It&amp;rsquo;s no surprise that the DHCP server ran out of resources since I see like 500+ devices around.
Hey, Leo Express, I am looking at you!
Luckily, not being able to connect to the internet I started hacking discovery image.</description></item><item><title>Foreman and PXE less environments</title><link>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2015-10-07-foreman-and-pxe-less-environments/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2015-10-07-foreman-and-pxe-less-environments/</guid><description>Foreman (and Satellite 6) has many options when it comes to provisioning in PXE-less (or DHCP-less) environments.
Option 1: Bootdisk plugin - iPXE
Foreman Bootdisk plugin enables Foreman users to download Host based or Generic host images. These are small ISO images pre-loaded with SYSLINUX which chainloads iPXE. This kind of firmware is able to load kernels via http, but hardware driver in iPXE must exist for this to work. Unfortunately, there are many issues with various hardware and even virtualization technologies (VMWare, Microsoft).</description></item><item><title>SELinux Puppet update in Fedora 20 and Rawhide</title><link>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2014-04-10-selinux-puppet-update-in-fedora-20-and-rawhide/</link><pubDate>Thu, 10 Apr 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2014-04-10-selinux-puppet-update-in-fedora-20-and-rawhide/</guid><description>We are rolling out update of Puppet to 3.4.3 in Fedora 20 and Rawhide that adds one important change. We have found that puppet master was running unconfined, therefore the Puppet SELinux policy was not effective in Fedoras.
The puppet package update fixes one little issue (missing runtime dependency) and corrects startup wrappers for systemd which puts Puppet Master into correct SELinux domain puppetmaster_t. Since this has low security impact, we have decided to backport this change into Fedora 20 too.</description></item><item><title>Extracting strings for gettext with Vim</title><link>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2013-04-03-extracting-strings-for-gettext-with-vim/</link><pubDate>Wed, 03 Apr 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2013-04-03-extracting-strings-for-gettext-with-vim/</guid><description>Big news today, I will be working on Foreman open-source project from now on. Recently I was working on Katello - subscription and package management system.
The Foreman is a complete lifecycle management tool for physical and virtual servers. More info at http://www.theforeman.org
I have been extracting strings today from the codebase for gettext support. If you don&amp;rsquo;t know what that, let me briefly describe it. I need to convert all &amp;ldquo;strings&amp;rdquo; or &amp;lsquo;strings&amp;rsquo; into the following format:</description></item></channel></rss>