<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>blog on Lukáš Zapletal</title><link>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/tags/blog/</link><description>Recent content in blog on Lukáš Zapletal</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 02 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://blog.zapletalovi.com/tags/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Improved the blog theme</title><link>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2016-12-02-improved-the-blog-theme/</link><pubDate>Fri, 02 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2016-12-02-improved-the-blog-theme/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;ve improved the navbar, it should now work on mobile devices. Thanks for reporting this.
I tried to update to Bootstrap 3 but it did not work well. I guess I will stay on the old version for now. Christmas time!</description></item><item><title>Served by CloudFlare</title><link>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2015-12-16-served-by-cloudflare/</link><pubDate>Wed, 16 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2015-12-16-served-by-cloudflare/</guid><description>Starting today, my blog is being served through CloudFlare caching CDN. This means faster loading speeds, but what&amp;rsquo;s more important is valid SSL certificate through their SSL Free Termination service. I will switch all links to https by default and after few weeks if there are no issues reported, I will force HTTPS via redirect.
https://sheharyar.me/blog/free-ssl-for-github-pages-with-custom-domains/
And yeah, my blog now supports HTTP/2 and SPDY and other fancy things.
Please report issues via discussion or IRC or Google+.</description></item><item><title>Blog migrated to github.com</title><link>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2012-07-24-migrated-to-github/</link><pubDate>Tue, 24 Jul 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2012-07-24-migrated-to-github/</guid><description>You maybe noticed some articles in your RSS reader are doubled and I apologize for that. I have successfully migrated to the new blog hosting and engine and switched the FeedBurner RSS source.
My blog is now just a bunch of static pages server by github.com pages and you may noticed is is quite fast. I use Jekyll for generating of the content. I was playing around with various addons and forks, but then I went for this plain approach together with Twitter Bootstrap template.</description></item><item><title>Moving my blog to github.com</title><link>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2012-07-23-moving-my-blog-to-githubcom/</link><pubDate>Mon, 23 Jul 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2012-07-23-moving-my-blog-to-githubcom/</guid><description>Guys, I am going to move my blog to github.com infrastructure. I will be using Jekyll templating framework, pages will be pregenerated with Twitter Bootstrap. Migration from Blogger.com was pretty straightforward, I will blog about it later on.
Nothing is gonna change for you, even URLs will remain the same, but please check if you have subscribed the correct RSS address. The correct one is:
http://feeds.feedburner.com/LukasZapletal
Wrong one is:</description></item><item><title>Komentáře nově na službě Disqus</title><link>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2011-02-22-komentare-nove-na-sluzbe-disqus/</link><pubDate>Tue, 22 Feb 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2011-02-22-komentare-nove-na-sluzbe-disqus/</guid><description>Přidal jsem na blog novou službu na komentování pod články. Doposud jsem používal strandardní Blogger widget, ale čím dál víc se na webu setkávám se službou Disqus. Zkusil jsem ji tedy "na test" a byl jsem nadšen. Takhle nějak si představuji software-as-service.
Instalace jedním klikem. A to doslova. Po registraci nového diskuzního prostoru stačilo klinout a nechat služby mezi sebou autorizovat. V návrháři na Bloggeru se mi objevil nový widget, který jsem si přesunul pod článek.</description></item><item><title>Měl jsem pět, ale zaplatím osm</title><link>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2010-06-10-mel-jsem-pet-ale-zaplatim-osm/</link><pubDate>Thu, 10 Jun 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2010-06-10-mel-jsem-pet-ale-zaplatim-osm/</guid><description>Je to k vzteku. Nedávno jsem rozjel nový blog, ale až včera jsem se od kamaráda dozvěděl, že mi nefunguje RSS feed. Chtěl jsem dát nějaký čas všem, aby si přečetli můj poslední příspěvek na starém blogu týkající se migrace a změny RSS adresy. A pak jsem jej pochopitelně zapomněl přepnout na nový feed.
Adresa zůstává stejná, jen jsem překonfiguroval Feed Burner, aby stahoval ze správné adresy (z Bloggeru). Opakování je matka moudrosti - adresa feedu je:</description></item></channel></rss>