<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>android on Lukáš Zapletal</title><link>https://blog.zapletalovi.com/tags/android/</link><description>Recent content in android on Lukáš Zapletal</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 13 Jul 2012 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.zapletalovi.com/tags/android/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Why the new game console OUYA is important</title><link>https://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2012-07-13-why-new-game-console-ouya-is-important/</link><pubDate>Fri, 13 Jul 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2012-07-13-why-new-game-console-ouya-is-important/</guid><description>You probably heard it already. An US-based (LA) company began a fund-raising campaign on Kickstarter with a goal of collecting $950,000 to transform its project from the prototype to a product. By today, pledges are totaling about $4.5 million and it's still raising.
I think it's big and I pledged ordering one. Then I started reading all the comments, reactions and articles. While most of them were very positive, there are few predicting failures or pointing out this is just a better Raspsberry PI with a controller.</description></item><item><title>Android on Acer Aspire One</title><link>https://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2011-09-16-android-on-acer-aspire-one/</link><pubDate>Fri, 16 Sep 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2011-09-16-android-on-acer-aspire-one/</guid><description>My mum bought a mowing machine few ears ago in Mountfield stores and they gave her Acer Aspire One netbook. Yeah for free - special action. But this is extraordinary piece of junk hardware - Atom CPU, 1 GB RAM, 1024×600 LCD screen and internal 16 GB compact flash card. All with preloaded Windows XP that can get you to the internet as fast as 8-9 minutes. Everything is hell slow, system has few minutes lags sometimes.</description></item><item><title>Android bez Javy dál válcuje konkurenci (LE)</title><link>https://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2010-08-20-android-bez-javy-dal-valcuje-konkurenci/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Aug 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2010-08-20-android-bez-javy-dal-valcuje-konkurenci/</guid><description>Na serveru LinuxEXPRES.cz vyšlo moje shrnutí o aktuální žalobě Oraclu proti společnosti Google s názvem Android bez Javy dál válcuje konkurenci. Komentujte.</description></item></channel></rss>