<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>english on Lukáš Zapletal</title><link>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/tags/english/</link><description>Recent content in english on Lukáš Zapletal</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 16 Mar 2011 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://blog.zapletalovi.com/tags/english/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Linux support on Intel D410PT</title><link>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2011-03-16-linux-support-on-intel-d410pt/</link><pubDate>Wed, 16 Mar 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2011-03-16-linux-support-on-intel-d410pt/</guid><description>There are some rumours about Intel D410PT Atom-based motherboard not working under Linux on the internet. Some user reported the board is not booting Linux-based CD-ROM, others are having problems with booting process getting stucked.
Ignoring the stuck boot process that is usually resolved by connecting a keyboard to the box the first problem has a simple solution. When product user manual v1.0 states it only support Windows XP/Vista/7 it does not mean there is no Linux support.</description></item><item><title>Proč najednou tolik jazyka anglického?</title><link>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2011-03-16-proc-najednou-toliko-jazyka-anglickeho/</link><pubDate>Wed, 16 Mar 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2011-03-16-proc-najednou-toliko-jazyka-anglickeho/</guid><description>Pravidelní čtenáři mé studnice různých technických nesmyslů, rad o které nikdo nestojí a expertíz od toho nejnepovolanějšího jistě zachytili zvýšený výskyt anglicky psaných příspěvků. Inu, důvod je možná prostější než by se mohlo zdát. A teďka - co z něj vypadne, co? :-)
Rapidně se mi zvýšil počet pravidelných čtenářů ze zahraničí, kteří jaksi neovládají jazyk český. Řekl bych -- tak to jsme na tom zhruba stejně. Když jsem se dozvěděl, že někteří používají Google Translate, tak mi jich bylo líto.</description></item><item><title>RHEL 6 and networking</title><link>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2011-03-15-rhel-6-and-networking/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Mar 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2011-03-15-rhel-6-and-networking/</guid><description>To someone surprise Red Hat Enterprise Linux 6 does not configure network when you do the default minimal installation. You can still make the Anaconda installer to do it for you but you need to hit Configure network button on the domain name setting page. If you forget you don't have a network. Tough luck.
Since RHEL6 use NetworkManager by default users that just installed text-only server can be surprised twice as their /etc/sysconfig/network-scripts/ifcfg-eth0 can look like:</description></item><item><title>Silence supp enable option on Cisco phones</title><link>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2011-02-18-silence-supp-enable-option-on-cisco/</link><pubDate>Fri, 18 Feb 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2011-02-18-silence-supp-enable-option-on-cisco/</guid><description>I use teleconferencing quite a lot in Red Hat. Got Cisco VoIP phone on my desk and Linksys at home. These phones have an option to suppress volume once it detects silence on the line. This can be nice option but during teleconferences we use, well we have to use, mute buttons because sometimes there are so many people that background noise would kill the meeting.
I have discovered having this option turned on can be troublesome.</description></item><item><title>Create self-signed certificate for Apache on one line</title><link>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2011-02-17-create-self-signed-certificate-for/</link><pubDate>Thu, 17 Feb 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2011-02-17-create-self-signed-certificate-for/</guid><description>You need to create a self-signed certificate for httpd server by Apache Software Foundation I guess. There are thousands of tutorials out there. But I have the special one. A oneliner. Yeah! Do the following in an empty directory, /tmp for example. openssl genrsa -out cert.key 1024 &amp;&amp; echo -ne "\n\n\n\n\n$HOSTNAME\nroot@$HOSTNAME\n" | openssl req -new -key cert.key -x509 -out cert.crt -days 999
All done. Nasty, isn't it? You can check out your fresh certificate by issuing</description></item><item><title>How to prepare a gemfile package for Fedora</title><link>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2011-01-31-how-to-prepare-gemfile-package-for/</link><pubDate>Mon, 31 Jan 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2011-01-31-how-to-prepare-gemfile-package-for/</guid><description>It's a piece of cake to create a gemfile RPM package using the gem2rpm tool, but Fedora Package Guidelines for Ruby compliance is not that straightforward. Let me explain basic issues a packager will be facing to.
The fist part is a duck soup. Really. Set the gem2rpm against downloaded gem file. Most likely you'll need to redirect it's standard output to a file. That's your starting point spec file.</description></item><item><title>X-Plane 9 and Intel GMA HD</title><link>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2010-12-28-x-plane-9-intel-gma-hd/</link><pubDate>Tue, 28 Dec 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2010-12-28-x-plane-9-intel-gma-hd/</guid><description>X-Plane 9 does not run well on Intel GMA graphics. I have tested it on GMA HD today. There are textures missing -- everything is just gray (TM). It turned out the problem is in lack of S3 texture compression algorithm in the Mesa 3D library which is used for 3D on all Intel graphics drivers.
Running X-Plane 9 with MESA_DEBUG=1 shows the actual problem: Mesa warning: couldn't open libtxc_dxtn.</description></item><item><title>Konverze symlinků na soubory</title><link>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2010-12-09-konverze-symlinku-na-soubory/</link><pubDate>Thu, 09 Dec 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2010-12-09-konverze-symlinku-na-soubory/</guid><description>Potřeboval jsem dnes převést větší množství symlinků na cílové soubory. Nenašel jsem ani po pěti minutách žádný program (tedy jeden ano - unln napsaný v Perlu který nefungoval), takže jsem si vytvořil tento skript. Stačí mu předat jeden nebo více symlinků a on je přepíše cílovými soubory. Třeba se to bude někomu hodit. Použití je snadné:
# ls ...
test_link -> /tmp/test_file
# unln test_link
# ls ...
test_file</description></item></channel></rss>