<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>katello on Luk치코 Zapletal</title><link>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/tags/katello/</link><description>Recent content in katello on Luk치코 Zapletal</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 25 Feb 2013 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://blog.zapletalovi.com/tags/katello/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Katello on Torquebox talk from Dev Conf 2013</title><link>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2013-02-25-katello-on-torquebox-talk-from-dev-conf-2013/</link><pubDate>Mon, 25 Feb 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2013-02-25-katello-on-torquebox-talk-from-dev-conf-2013/</guid><description>Hey all, I am happy to publish my talk I have yesterday on Developer Conference 2013 in Brno. Slides are available on-line in html format.
And also as PDF on the SlideShare.net:
I was talking about proof of concept port of Katello to JRuby. I had several issues with rubygem slow loading, bundler and rvm. The actual port was pretty smooth and I was giving several tips for JRuby porting, in particular for Ruby on Rails applications.</description></item><item><title>Writing katello upgrade script</title><link>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2012-11-28-writing-katello-upgrade-script/</link><pubDate>Wed, 28 Nov 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2012-11-28-writing-katello-upgrade-script/</guid><description>With Katello, we deliver script upgrade-katello which enables users to upgrade to the latest version interactively. Each upgrade is divided into several steps. To see all of them, do:
# ls /usr/share/katello/install/upgrade-scripts/ -1 0050_start_qpid.sh 0099_preallocate_mongo.sh 0100_start_mongodb.sh 0110_migrate_pulp.sh 0200_start_httpd.sh 0385_remove_hornet_files.sh 0390_migrate_candlepin.sh 0400_start_tomcat.sh 0410_start_elasticsearch.sh 0700_start_foreman.sh 0710_migrate_katello.sh 0711_reindex_elastic.sh 0720_create_foreman_users.rb 0800_start_katello.sh 0805_start_katello_jobs.sh 0900_katello_configure.sh Each step is just an linux executable, most of them are simple bash scripts with shebang and header which is parsed by the katello-upgrade script:</description></item><item><title>Rsync in cron</title><link>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2012-07-19-rsync-in-cron/</link><pubDate>Thu, 19 Jul 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2012-07-19-rsync-in-cron/</guid><description>I've installed some rsync scripts to a RHEL6 cron yesterday, but this morning I was surprised with error messages in my mailbox:
/etc/bashrc: fork: retry: Resource temporarily unavailable
/etc/bashrc: fork: Resource temporarily unavailable
rsync: connection unexpectedly closed (0 bytes received so far) [receiver]
When you see resource temporarily unavailable you can be sure it is most likely some system limit issue, or your box is really running out of resources (worse case).</description></item><item><title>RHN Subscription Management in RHEL 6</title><link>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2011-08-27-how-to-use-rhn-certificate-based/</link><pubDate>Sat, 27 Aug 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2011-08-27-how-to-use-rhn-certificate-based/</guid><description>Prominent change in the new Red Hat Enterprise Linux 6.1 is brand new subscription management. While RHEL 6.1 still include the classic RHN tools and commands (rhn_register, rhnreg_ks and others), it is also possible to use the new RHN Certificate-Based Subscription Management. In this article, I am going to go through all the required steps of sucessful registration and subscription of a RHEL 6.1 system.
First of all make sure you did not use the classic RHN before you procced with the tutorial.</description></item><item><title>Red Hat Update Infrastructure 2.0</title><link>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2011-08-22-red-hat-update-infrastructure-20/</link><pubDate>Mon, 22 Aug 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2011-08-22-red-hat-update-infrastructure-20/</guid><description>Last month Red Hat released Red Hat Update Infrastructure 2.0. It is a collection of technologies that offers cloud providers the ability to easily deploy Red Hat solutions into their environments. Cloud solution providers can use Red Hat Update Infrastructure to give their customers the ability to update Red Hat technology in the cloud.
Red Hat Update Infrastructure streamlines the deployment of Red Hat technologies into a cloud environment. Initial configuration, initialization, and synchronization of available instances in the cloud are done with very little user configuration or intervention.</description></item><item><title>Announcing project Katello</title><link>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2011-06-20-announcing-project-katello/</link><pubDate>Mon, 20 Jun 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://blog.zapletalovi.com/posts/2011-06-20-announcing-project-katello/</guid><description>We are announcing the opening of the Katello project. Katello is an open source system management platform and will be the upstream project for Red Hat System Engine, a component of the larger CloudForms product. System Engine is the subscription, content, and configuration engine for CloudForms. It will focus on a system's lifecycle similar to what the RHN Satellite product does today.
Katello is designed as an orchestration layer over best-of-breed projects: Pulp for Content Management, Foreman for Configuration Management, and Candlepin for Susbcription Management.</description></item></channel></rss>